Chic Young Cartoons
Chic Young Cartoons
1929-1934
Young, Chic, 1901-1973
2.5 linear ft.
Original cartoons from the newspaper comic strips Blondie, Dumb Dora, The Family Foursome and When Mother Was a Girl.
148780
Biographical History
Murat Bernard Young (1901-1973), famously known as Chic Young, was an American cartoonist and creator of the newspaper comic strip Blondie.
Chic Young was born in Chicago, Illinois, and grew up St. Louis, Missouri. He returned to Chicago to study at the Chicago Art Institute, lived briefly in Cleveland where he drew The Affairs of Jane for the NEA syndicate, and then landed in New York in 1922. His first strip there, Beautiful Bab for the Bell Syndicate, earned him a job offer from King Features Syndicate.
His first strip for King, in 1924, was Dumb Dora. In April of 1930, Young turned this strip over to Paul Fung so that he could devote himself to his new creation, the strip for which he is best known—Blondie. (One notes a pattern: Young had a knack for drawing pretty girls!) The strip, over the course of its long run, took Blondie from a flighty single girl with several beaux to marriage and children with Dagwood Bumstead and, eventually, a career as a caterer. The strip and its characters were aggressively and cleverly marketed, which resulted in 28 movies starring Arthur Lake and Penny Singleton as well as a radio show and a television series. Several artists worked with Young on Blondie over the years, including Alex Raymond, Ray McGill, and Jim Raymond. Young's son Dean eventually took the strip over on his father's death.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Chic Young Cartoons collection contains 12 original daily cartoons and 5 original Sunday cartoons from the comic strip Blondie (1934). The collection also contains 1 original Sunday cartoon from the Blondie topper strip The Family Foursome (this title ran with the Sunday feature)(1934). In addition, there are 4 original Sunday cartoons from the comic strip Dumb Dora (1929-1930) and 3 original examples of its topper strip, When Mother Was a Girl (1929).
Please note that some of the large format Sunday cartoons are complete in two pieces; some of our holdings are partial (only 1 of 2 pieces). See Inventory for details.
Arrangement of the Collection
The cartoons are arranged in alphabetical order by title, then chronologically. The daily Blondie cartoons are foldered separately at the head of the collection.
Related Material
See the
Paul Fung Cartoons
collection for additional material related to Dumb Dora and When Mother Was a Girl. See the
C. D. Russell Cartoons
collection for additional material related to Blondie. has collections of more than 150 cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Young, Chic, 1901-1973.; King Features Syndicate.; Blondie (comic strip); Dumb Dora (comic strip); Family foursome (comic strip); When mother was a girl (comic strip); Art -- Cartoonists; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Comic books, strips, etc. -- United States.; Cartoons (humorous images); Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Kenneth Rendell, 1968.
Inventory
- Blondie, 1934; 17
  - Daily cartoons, 12; (blue pencil, pen and ink on illustration board, approx. 5 ½ x 21 in.)
    - August 3, 1934 (Box 1)
    - August 4, 1934 (Box 1)
    - August 7, 1934 (Box 1)
    - August 9, 1934 (Box 1)
    - August 10, 1934 (Box 1)
    - August 11, 1934 (Box 1)
    - August 13, 1934 (Box 1)
    - August 16, 1934 (Box 1)
    - August 17, 1934 (Box 1)
    - August 18, 1934 (Box 1)
    - August 20, 1934 (Box 1)
    - August 24, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Sunday cartoons, 5; (blue pencil, pen and ink on illustration board, dimensions vary)
    - August 5, 1934, (partial/1 piece)(7 x 21 ½ in.) (Box 1)
    - August 12, 1934, (partial/1 piece)(7 x 21 ½ in.) (Box 1)
    - August 19, 1934, (complete/2 pieces)(17 ½ x 21 ½ in.) (Box 1)
    - August 26, 1934, (partial/1 piece)(7 x 21 ½ in.) (Box 1)
    - September 9, 1934, (partial/1 piece)(9 ½ x 21 ½ in.) (Box 1)
- Dumb Dora, 1929-1930; 4
  - Sunday cartoons, (blue pencil, pen and ink on illustration board, approx. 19 x 23 in.)
    - October 20, 1929, (complete/2 pieces) (Box 1)
    - October 27, 1929, (complete/2 pieces) (Box 1)
    - March 2, 1930, (complete/2 pieces) (Box 1)
    - March 16, 1930, (complete/2 pieces) (Box 1)
- The Family Foursome, 1934; 1
  - Sunday cartoons, (traces of graphite, pen and ink on illustration board, approx. 9 ½ x 21 ½ in.)
    - August 5, 1934, (complete/1 piece)(w/ Blondie "Paper Doll Review") (Box 1)
- When Mother Was a Girl, 1929-1930; 3
  - Sunday cartoons, (traces of graphite, pen and ink on illustration board, dimensions vary)
    - October 27, 1929, (complete/1 piece)(9 ¼ x 23 in.) (Box 1)
    - November 24, 1929, (complete/1 piece)(7 x 19 ¼ in.) (Box 1)
    - March 16, 1930, (complete/1 piece)(7 x 23 in.) (Box 1)